Finding Aid for University of Michigan Photographs Vertical File ca. 1817-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University of Michigan Photographs Vertical File
1850s-1980s
Bentley Historical Library (collector)
92147 UBImus UBImum UBImul
Photographs collected from various sources, depicting buildings, faculty, students, and other topics relating to the University of Michigan.
11.25 linear feet
25 oversize drawers
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The University of Michigan Photographs Vertical file has been assembled from various sources.
The collection is open for research.
The University of Michigan Photographs Vertical file is organized in eight categories or series based in part on a classification system developed for the printed and photograph vertical file. The series are listed below along with the major subdivisions in each:
Administration Central Administration Business Offices and Miscellaneous Services Faculty Administration
Academic and Support Units Colleges and Schools Summer Sessions Libraries Museums
History and Description General Campus Views Campus Buildings
Special Celebrations and Events Commencements Inaugurals Anniversaries Special Events Emergencies and War
Student Life and Customs General [Student organizations] Honorary Societies and Professional Societies Housing Social Fraternities and Sororities Student Celebrations and Carnivals Intercollegiate Sports
Class Photos, 1858-1956 Classes by Year: Group Portraits and Reunions Classes by Year: Individual Portraits
Affiliated and Associated Organizations
The University of Michigan Photographs Vertical File represents a miscellaneous assemblage of U of M-related photographs from many different sources, mainly prior to 1950. The vertical file is especially strong on the earliest photographic images of the campus, university buildings, and class activities. While the vertical file contains many images of individuals, researchers should first consult the library's on-line catalog for images of faculty, administrators, and other University personalities. Most photographs originally accumulated by a University department or other unit are kept with that unit's records.
The arrangement of the photographic images was intended to parallel the classification used with University of Michigan published materials and with manuscript materials. Both of these used a classification system using letters of the alphabet (A through N only) for groupings of published or manuscript material. This system was carried over for use with the library's photographic images though there are certain categories for which images are unlikely to be found (Category A, for example, which pertains to legislation affecting the University or Category I which is reserved for university publications of a scientific or literary nature). The classification is further broken down under each letter by a number code which refers to a more specific subdivision. The heaviest concentration of images will be found under C (for U-M schools and colleges, departments, and other units), D (for university buildings and views), and F (for class pictures, photos of student organizations, and images detailing aspects of student life and customs).
Each heading in this finding aid includes the letter classification plus a numbered subdivision. In addition, the individual envelopes are numbered sequentially. Headings for which there are oversized images (usually larger than 8x10) will be indicated by reference to medium or large size photographs. When requesting material, researchers must specify the heading and the classification and folder number.
This finding aid describes only a small portion of the Bentley Library's U-M visual images. The on-line catalog will direct the researcher to additional images.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Astronomical observatories.; Catholepistemiad (Detroit, Mich.); Horace H. Rackham Educational Memorial (Detroit, Mich.); Hospitals--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Laboratories.; Libraries--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Medicine--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Sports.Sports.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan--Buildings.Buildings.; University of Michigan--Campus.Campus.; University of Michigan--Classes.Classes.; University of Michigan--Commencements.Commencements.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan--Honorary societies.Honorary societies.; University of Michigan--Presidents.Presidents.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae--Anniversaries, etc.Alumni and alumnaeAnniversaries, etc.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.StudentsSocieties, etc.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.StudentsSocial life and customs.; University of Michigan--Student housing.Student housing.; Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.; Classrooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Dancing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; World War, 1914-1918--Education and the war.; World War, 1914-1918--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; World War, 1939-1945--Education and the war.; World War, 1939-1945--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre/Form:
Aerial photographs.; Photographs.
- Administration
  The Administration series includes both formal and informal group and individual portraits of university central administration and support staff and some office and workplace images.
  - Central Administration
    - Board of Regents (Folder B2-1)
      also medium and large
    - President: Miscellaneous (Folder B3)
      medium and large only
    - Fleming Administration (Folder B3)
      medium only
      (catalogued separately)
    - Secretary (Folder B4-2)
    - Registrar (Folder B5-3)
    - Deans (Folder B7-7)
  - Special Scholarships
    - Barbour Scholarships for Oriental Women, 3 folders (Folder B17)
      (catalogued separately); medium only
  - Service Units
    - Business Offices, Miscellaneous (Folder B27-8)
    - Janitors (Folder B27-9)
    - Plant Department Equipment (Folder B27-10)
    - Bureau of Appointments and Occupational Information (Folder B29-11)
  - Faculty Administration
    - Administrative Board (Folder B31-12)
    - Distinguished Service Medal (Folder B31-13)
    - Faculty, 3 envelopes (Folder B31-14-16)
- Academic and Support Units
  Photos in the Academic and Support Units series include college and department faculty and staff portraits, classroom scenes, laboratories and other facilities, and a variety of academic and research activities.
  - Colleges and Schools
    - College of Literature, Science, and the Arts (1841)
      - Anthropology Department (Folder C26-23)
      - Botany Department (Folder C26-24)
      - Chemistry Department, 2 folders (Folder C26-25/26)
      - Economics Department (Folder C26-27)
      - Far Eastern Languages and Literatures Department (Folder C26-28)
      - Japanese Studies, Center for (Folder C26-29)
      - Physics Department (Folder C26-30)
      - Psychology Department (Folder C26-31)
      - Zoology Department (Folder C26-32)
    - Medical School (1850)
      - Medical School Miscellaneous (Folder C41-33)
        also medium
      - Medical School, 7 folders (Folder C46)
        (catalogued separately); medium and large only
      - Kresge Hearing Research Institute (Folder C46-34)
      - Ophthalmology Department (Folder C46-35)
      - Pathology Department (Folder C46-36)
      - Physiology Department (Folder C46-37)
      - Alumni reunion, 1860s graduates (Folder C56-38)
    - Law School
      - Law School (1859) (Folder C61-39)
    - College of Pharmacy (1868)
      - College of Pharmacy, 2 folders (Folder C81)
        (catalogued separately; large only)
      - Pharmacy Laboratories (Folder C81-40)
      - Pharmacy Miscellaneous (Folder C81-41)
      - Pharmacy Students (Folder C81-42)
    - Homeopathic Medical School (1875)
      - Dr. Kinyon performing surgery in the amphitheatre, 1908/09 (Folder C101-43)
      - Faculty and students (Folder C101-44)
      - Nurses and nurses' quarters (Folder C101-45)
      - Surgery, clinics, and wards (Folder C101-46)
    - School of Dentistry (1875)
      - School of Dentistry (Folder C121-47)
    - College of Engineering (1895)
      - College of Engineering (Folder C141-48)
      - Engineering shops and laboratories-Interiors, 3 folders (Folder C146-49-51)
    - Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies
      - Institute for Human Adjustment (Folder C170-51a)
      - Institute of Public Administration (Folder C170-51b)
    - College of Architecture and Design (1913)
      [became College of Architecture and Urban Planning and School of Art, 1974]
      - College of Architecture and Design (Folder C181-52)
    - School of Education (1921)
      - Center for the Study of Higher Education (Folder C206-53)
      - University High School (Folder C217-54)
      - University Elementary School (Folder C219-55)
    - School of Forestry and Conservation (1927)
      [became School of Natural Resources, 1950]
      - School of Natural Resources (Folder C241-56)
      - May Musicale. (Folder C241-57)
      - Saginaw Forest (Folder C246-58)
    - School of Nursing (1941)
      - School of Nursing (Folder C261-58a)
      - Nurses Alumni Association (Folder C276-ML)
    - School of Music (1929)
      - School of Music (Folder C321-59)
      - Stanley quartet (Folder C328-60)
    - School of Library Science (1969)
      - School of Library Science (Folder C641-96)
  - Summer Session
    - Summer Session: General (Folder C361-61)
    - Summer Camps (Folder C367)
      - Biological Station (Folder C367-62)
        also large
      - Camp Davis (Folder C367-63)
      - National Music Camp, Interlochen (Folder C327)
        large only
    - Fresh Air camp (Folder C367-64)
  - Libraries
    - Library Extension Service, 3 envelopes (Folder C410-65-67)
      (cataloged separately, Box 57 of Library Extension Service records)
    - General Library (1883-1918) Interiors (Folder C416-68)
    - General (Graduate) Library (1920-)
      - Interiors (Folder C419-69)
      - Bindery (Folder C419)
      - Special collections (Folder C420-70)
      - Staff (Folder C424-71)
    - Branch Libraries- (Folder C430)
      - Chemistry (Folder C430-72)
      - Engineering (Folder C430-73)
      - North Campus Stacks (Folder C430-74)
    - Law Library (Haven Hall, ) Interiors, 1863-1931 (Folder C435-75)
    - Law Library (Legal Research Building, 1931-) Interiors (Folder C435-76)
    - William L. Clements Library (Folder C440-77)
  - Museums, Observatories, botanical gardens
    - Geology (Natural Science Building) (Folder C450-78)
    - Museum of Art: Gallery in General Library (1883-1910), 2 folders (Folder C450-79-80)
    - Museum of Art: Alumni Memorial Hall (1910-) (Folder C450-81)
    - Natural History Museum: Mason Hall (1856-1880) (Folder C450-82)
    - Herbarium (Folder C450-83)
    - The Stearns Collection (musical instruments) (Folder C450-84)
    - University Museums Staff (Anthropology, Paleontology, Zoology) (Folder C450-85)
    - Observatory (Folder C455-86)
    - Nichols Arboretum; Botanical Gardens (Folder C457-88)
  - Off-campus Colleges and Branches
    - Branches of the University: 1837-1850 (Pontiac, Kalamazoo) (Folder C469-89)
    - Dearborn Center (Folder C469-90)
    - Flint Center (Folder C469-90a)
  - Extension Service
    - Extension Service (Folder C470-M)
  - Service Units
    - Radio Station WCBN (Folder C471-91)
    - Information Services (Folder C475-92)
  - Medical Center (Folder C500-93)
  - Laboratories and Institutes
    - Willow Run Laboratories (Folder C540-94)
    - Institute of Archaeological Research (Folder C420-93a)
    - Institute for Social Research (Folder C535-93b)
    - Highway Safety Research Institute (Transportation Research Institute) (Folder C547-94a)
    - Institute of Science and Technology (Folder C551-94b)
- History and Description
  The History and Description series documents the physical development of the campus. It includes aerial and panoramic views of campus, photos of individual buildings and photos of several university symbols such as the mace and seal.
  - General history and description (by subject)
    - Chapel (Folder D1-97)
    - Mace (Folder D1-98)
    - Seal (Folder D1-99)
  - Campus Views
    - General Views
      - Aerial views, central campus and hospital area together (Folder D2-100)
      - Construction, unidentified buildings (Folder D2-101)
      - From the Boulevard (Folder D2-102)
      - Miscellaneous buildings, 2 folders (Folder D2-103-104)
    - Central Campus
      - Aerial views (Folder D2-105)
        (also medium and large)
      - Campus walks, 2 folders (Folder D2-106-107)
      - Diagonal at northwest corner of campus
        - With fenceposts, 2 folders (Folder D2-108-109)
        - Without fenceposts showing, before 1893, 2 folders (Folder D2-110-111)
        - After 1898 (Folder D2-112)
      - Cathole (Folder D13-151)
      - East University area (Folder D2-113)
      - Flagpole area (Folder D2-114)
      - Mall (Ingalls Street) (Folder D2-115)
      - Miscellaneous views (Folder D2-116)
      - North University area (Folder D2-117)
      - State Street and North University area seen from campus (Folder D2-118)
      - State Street side of campus
        - From between North and South University (Folder D2-119)
        - From corner of North University and State (Folder D2)
        - 1863 - 1872 and undatable (Folder D2-120)
        - 1865 Print (Folder D2-120.5)
        - 1872 - 1893 (Folder D2-121)
        - 1893 - 1898 (Folder D2-122)
        - From corner of North University and State, 1898-1924 (Folder D2-123)
        - From corner of South University and State (Folder D2-124)
    - Medical Center
      - Aerial Views (Folder D2-125)
      - Catherine Street area (Folder D2-126)
      - University Hospital (Ann and Observatory) area (Folder D2-127)
    - North Campus
      - General views (Folder D2-128)
      - Planning and construction (Folder D2-129)
  - History by period
    - Catholepistemiad, 1817-1837 (Folder D3a-130)
  - Proposed buildings
    - Burton Tower and Music School (Folder D12-131)
    - University Hall (1838-1840) (Folder D12-132)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder D12-133)
  - Campus Buildings
    Campus Buildings includes exterior and some interior views of buildings and in many cases views of building construction. Interiors depicting specific classrooms, offices, and laboratories are filed in the Academic and Support Units series under the name of the unit pictured. Sculpture, monuments and other campus landmarks are included in this subseries. Buildings are filed under their latest or last name, with cross-references from earlier names. In a few cases, when the name of a building was changed shortly before it was torn down, the building is filed under its most common name.
    - [Adelia Cheever House (1947-1965) see Landscape Architecture Building]
    - [Administration Building (built 1948) see Literature, Science and the Arts Building]
    - [Administration Building (built 1968) see Fleming Administration Building]
    - Alexander G. Ruthven building (Folder D13-134)
    - Alice Crocker Lloyd Hall (Folder D13-135)
    - Alumnae House (1219 Washtenaw) (Folder D13-136)
    - Alumni Center (Folder D13-136.5)
    - Alumni Memorial Hall (Museum of Art), 2 folders (Folder D13-137-138)
    - Anatomical Laboratory (Folder D13-139)
    - Angell Hall (Folder D13-140)
    - [Architecture and Design Building (built 1928) see Lorch Hall]
    - [Athletic Administration Building (built 1912) see Women's Athletic Building]
    - [Baird Carillon see Burton Memorial Tower]
    - [Baits Houses see Vera Baits Houses]
    - Barbour Gymnasium [see also Waterman Gymnasium] (Folder D13-141)
    - Beal Residence (built 1906) (Folder D13-142)
    - [Bell Pool see Margaret Bell Pool]
    - Betsy Barbour House (Folder D13-143)
    - Boathouse (Argo Pond) (Folder D13-144)
    - [Boilerhouse (built 1879, near University Hall) see Heating Plant]
    - Boilerhouse (built 1884, near West Engineering Building) (Folder D13-145)
    - [Boilerhouse (built 1894) see R.O.T.C. Building]
    - [Botanical Gardens (1897-1906) see Library, Views from southeast and northeast]
    - Burton Memorial Tower and Charles Baird Carillon, 2 folders (Folder D13-146-147)
    - Business Administration Building, 2 folders (Folder D13-148-149)
    - Catherine Street Parking Structure (Folder D13-150)
    - Center for Research on Conflict Resolution (Folder D13-152)
    - Central Energy Plant (built 1914) (Folder D13-153)
    - [Charles Baird Carillon see Burton Memorial Tower]
    - [Chemical Laboratory (built 1856) see Economics Building]
    - Chemistry Building (built 1909), 2 folders (Folder D13-154-155)
    - Chrysler Center for Continuing Engineering Education (Folder D13-156)
    - Clarence C. Little Science Building (built 1925) (Folder D13-157)
    - [Clements Library see William L. Clements Library]
    - Coliseum (Folder D13-158)
    - Contagious Disease Hospital (Folder D13-159)
    - Convalescent Ward (Folder D13-160)
    - [Cooley Building see Mortimer E. Cooley Building]
    - Counseling Center (1007 E. Huron) (Folder D13-161)
    - Couzens Hall (Folder D13-162)
    - Crisler Arena (Folder D13-163)
    - [Dana Building see Samuel Trask Dana Natural Resources Building]
    - David M. Denison Physics and Astronomy Building (Folder D13-164)
    - Dental Building (1875-1879)
      (see Psychological Laboratory)
    - [Dental Building (1879-1891, on South University Avenue)]
      see Engineering Building (built 1840)
    - Dental Building (on North University Avenue), 1891-1908
      - (Pavilion Hospital), 1877-1891 (Folder D13-165)
      - (Pavilion Hospital with amphitheatre wing), 1879-1891 (Folder D13-166)
      - 1891-1908 (Folder D13-166)
        [In 1908 part of this building was moved to East University Avenue and renamed Surveying Building. See that heading for photos after 1908.]
    - Dental Building (built 1908) (Folder D13-168)
    - [Dental Building (built 1971) see School of Dentistry]
    - Dermatology Ward (Folder D13-169)
    - [Detroit Observatory see Observatory]
    - [East Convalescent Ward see Institute for Social Research (Catherine Street)]
    - East Engineering Building (Folder D13-170)
    - [East Hospital (built 1906) see Beal Residence]
    - [East Medical Building see Clarence C. Little Science Building]
    - East Medical Center Parking Structure (Folder D13-171)
    - [East Physics Building see Harrison M. Randall Laboratory]
    - East Quadrangle (Residential College) (Folder D13-172)
    - Economics Building
      - 1856-1880 (One story, with additions) (Folder D13-173)
      - 1880-1901 (Two stories) (Folder D13-174)
      - 1901-1956 (Pharmacology, northwest wing) (Folder D13-175)
      - Illustrations from (History of the Chemical Laboratory), by Edward D. Campbell (Folder D13-176)
      - 1908-1981 (Economics, south wing) (Folder D13-177)
      - 1981 fire (Folder D13-178)
    - Edward Henry Kraus Natural Science Building
      - Construction (Folder D13-179-180)
      - Exterior views (Folder D13-181)
    - [Engineering Annex see West Engineering Annex]
    - Engineering Building (built 1840)
      - 1879-1891 (original building with east wing) (Folder D13-182)
      - 1891-1922 (rebuilt as three-story building) (Folder D13-183)
    - [Engineering Building (built 1881) see Mechanical Engineering Laboratory]
    - Engineering Laboratory (built 1885) see West Engineering Annex]
    - Engineering Laboratory (built 1894) see R.O.T.C. Building]
    - [Engineering Research Annex (1219 Washtenaw) see Alumnae House]
    - [Engineering Shops (built 1885) see West Engineering Annex]
    - Ferry Field (Folder D13-184)
    - Fleming Administration Building (Folder D13-M)
    - Fletcher Street Parking Structure (Folder D13-185)
    - [Francis School of Public Health Building see Thomas Francis Jr. School of Public Health Building]
    - [Frieze Memorial Organ see University Hall: Interiors]
    - [Geodesy and Surveying Building see Surveying Building]
    - Gerald R. Ford Library), 2 folders (Folder D13-186-187)
    - Gordon Hall (Folder D13-188)
    - Harlan Hatcher Graduate Library
      - Construction (Folder D13-189)
      - Exteriors (Folder D13-190)
    - Harris Hall (Folder D13-191)
    - Harrison M. Randall Laboratory (Folder D13-192)
    - Haven Hall (built 1863)
      - 1863-1893 (Original building), 2 folders (Folder D13-193-194)
      - 1893-1898 (North wing with tower) (Folder D13-195)
      - 1898-1950 (South wing added, tower removed) (Folder D13-196-197)
      - 1950 fire (Folder D13-198)
    - Haven Hall (built 1952) (Folder D13-199)
    - [Health Service (1922-1940) see Museums Annex]
    - Health Service (built 1940) (Folder D13-200)
    - Heating Plant (built 1879), near University Hall) (Folder D13-201)
    - [Heating Plant (built 1894) see R.O.T.C Building]
    - [Heating Plant (built 1914) see Central Energy Plant]
    - Helen Newberry Residence (Folder D13-202)
    - Henry F. Vaughan Public Health Building (Folder D13-203)
    - Hill Auditorium, 2 folders (Folder D13-204-205)
    - [Hobart Hall see Harris Hall]
    - [Homeopathic Hospital (1879-1899) see Psychological Laboratory]
    - [Homeopathic Hospital (built 1891) see Convalescent Ward]
    - [Homeopathic Hospital (built 1900) see North Hall]
    - [Homeopathic Hospital Administration Building see Internes Home]
    - Horace H. Rackham Educational Memorial Building (Detroit)
      - Exteriors (Folder D13-206)
      - Interiors (Folder D13-207)
    - [Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies see Rackham Building]
    - Inglis House (Folder D13-208)
    - Institute for Social Research Building (Catherine Street, built 1891) (Folder D13-209)
    - Institute for Social Research Building (Thompson Street, built 1966) (Folder D13-210)
    - Internes Home / Nurses Home (see also North Hall) (Folder D13-211)
    - Intramural Sports Building (Folder D13-212)
    - [James B. Angell Hall see Angell Hall]
    - [Kellogg Foundation Institute see W.K. Kellogg Foundation Institute]
    - Kelsey Museum of Archaeology
      - Construction (Folder D13-213)
      - Exterior views (Folder D13-214)
    - [Kraus Building see Edward Henry Kraus Natural Science Building]
    - Kresge Hearing Research Institute (Folder D13-215)
    - Landscape Architecture Building (730 Hill Street) (Folder D13-216)
    - Laundry (Folder D13-217)
    - [Law Building (built 1863) see Haven Hall]
    - Law Quadrangle, 2 folders (Folder D13-218-219)
    - Legal Research Building (Folder D13-220)
    - Library (built 1883)
      - Views from north (Folder D13-221)
      - Views from northwest, 2 folders also medium (Folder D13-222-223)
      - Views from southeast and northeast, including views of Botanical Gardens (Folder D13-224)
      - Views from west and south (Folder D13-224)
      - Views from west and south. (Folder D13-225)
      - Razing of clock tower, 1918 (Folder D13-226)
    - [Library (built 1920) see Harlan Hatcher Graduate Library]
    - Literature, Science and the Arts Building (Folder D13-227)
    - [Little Science Building see Clarence C. Little Science Building]
    - [Lloyd Hall see Alice Crocker Lloyd Hall]
    - Lorch Hall (Folder D13-228)
    - [Lydia Mendelssohn Theatre see Michigan League]
    - McMath-Hulbert Observatory (Folder D13-229)
    - McMillan Hall (Folder D13-230)
    - The Mall (Folder D13-231)
    - Margaret Bell Pool (Folder D13-232)
    - Martha Cook Building (Folder D13-233)
    - [Mary Markley House (1219 Washtenaw) see Alumnae House] (Folder D13-)
    - Mason Hall (built 1841) (Folder D13-234)
    - Maternity Hospital
    - Mechanical Engineering Laboratory (built 1881) (Folder D13-235)
    - [Mechanical Laboratory (built 1885) see West Engineering Annex]